wanting of sensual objects or rather
wanting of objects you derived pleasure
from on the level of senses that
potential cares it's that mounting so in
order to abandon sexuality you have to
stop being concerned with the objects
that you want and start developing not
wanting of that wanting of the objects
of senses of course the restraint needs
to be done first and then on the basis
of that you can start discerning the
nature of wanting of anything pretty
much sensual not this well manifested
through this of that but overall it aims
at anything that will give you the
central pleasure sight sound smell taste
touches but for as long as you just if
you if you remain just focused with the
objects that you want you're failing to
see the root of that sensuality but
consequently if you develop not wanting
in regard to wanting of sense objects
that's how you also become the sense
object you lose concern with them
because you are proved to them through
developing not wanting of their wanting
so X sensuality is the wanting of
central objects welcoming is good would
say he welcome sensuality and gave
entertains a delight in it there would
be you wanting and accepting that
wanting of sense object at face value so
a scale monk a person who practices
correctly will then first be restrained
of course and then start seeing that
it's that bonding that's the problem
and then knowledge know the central
objects wanting is in regard to its
wanting of the sensual objects so that's
what he should not welcome entertain the
lighting so to not work welcoming
entertaining delighting the wanting of
the central objects you surmount the
whole domain of sensuality which is
central and wanting of them so that for me when
and wanting of them so that for me when
I say develop the not wanting of wanting
of sense essential objects that's what
it means don't delight don't entertain
don't welcome the wanting of sensual
objects and that wanting of sexual
objects see a person who doesn't see
this will be either concerned with
central objects denying them telling all
it's ugly it's ugly it's impermanent see
permanent basically miss miss supplying
his efforts so what sense objects
failing to see that they're rooted in in
being wanted that's the problem they
themselves are not problem but then
equally he then he tried to override
that initial wanting of sensual objects
try to get rid of it try to prevent it
from arising but you can't do that
because that's not on you as the Buddha
said the eye wants to see the
plasmasites ear no smell nose wants to
smell ear wants to hear body wants to
touch that's just the structural
experience that's the five senses that's
how they open it that's what we'll refer
is feeding grounds so trying to
interfere with that wanting of your
sense objects is also taking it up
exactly exactly so and that's some that
off the people will misunderstand with
the Buddha said you don't delight you
don't welcome don't entertain it does
not mean you deny that first arising
means you see it as a whole you see that
there is the sense objects that are
being wanted by the senses basically and
that's what you don't delight in that's
what you don't want you don't want to
entertain the wanting of sensuality but
if wanting of sensuality has a reason
it's gonna persist on its own as in
arisen Dhamma as in the recent phenomena
for as long as it persists your only
concern is to not delight in it not
welcome it not hesitated for any time
during that duration at any point in
that duration you always remain no but I
don't want that it remains unwanted so
like somebody comes in front of your
door and once
come in but the only way to come in is
if you welcome it and let it in so in
the beginning you might feel awkward and
pressured and and nervous cuz it's there
it's it from the door what if what if
what if and then you had to go out or
you welcome them out of the weakness or
the engagement one way or the other but
if you realize well wait a minute you
can't come in it can stand there for you
for hundreds of years even once that's
not my concern my concern is to not
welcoming inside that's it that's it and
surprise surprise if you stop practicing
like that it will go away on its own
that's like the mottos daughters they're
gonna try and come and harass you for as
long as they perceive a way in a
possibility of being allowed to come
inside and that's when they tried with
the Buddha after his enlightenment and
there was nothing they couldn't get in
and then the martyr told him off like oh
I've been trying for years and you think
you're gonna but yeah for those who
don't practice like that it's enough to
just stand in front of the door and the
person will cave in and start to engage
out of whatever pressuring and
uncomfortable over and over but if you
recognizes no all I have to do is keep
the door closed not like I try to chase
them away because that would be engaging
with them affirming or denying either
way you engage with it so the only way
to engage is not engage sorry is to
allow it to arise whichever way wants to
rise and then not welcome it
don't open the door don't entertain it
don't engage with it and if you do that
to the extent necessary as in for the
sufficient amount of time it will stop
coming and that's how the other suitors
we talked about and read like you
established your mind in the
imperturbable in regard to sensuality
because we took whether your sight sound
smell taste touch where is that this
will it's past future present doesn't
matter you're not concerned with the
content of it you just maintain the
attitude of not wanting the reason
wanting of these sense objects that's it
and if you do that to fish amount of
time the arising of the wanting of sense
objects it's gonna change it
significance it's not gonna be about
sense objects of anymore it's gonna be
about oh this is that which is not
welcomed this is that which is not
delighted this is that which is not
wanted this is that which used to be my
sensuality basically used to mean used
to mean go after these objects because
they are wanted and you took that at a
face value well don't go after this
thing because they're not wanted and you
took that at a face value or rather you
wanted the absence of these things and
you took that want to get the face value
but now you stop welcoming stop
entertaining you stopped wanting the
wanting of the sense objects while the
objects remain the same the whole domain
remain the same the eyes still have
their feeding grounds but now you
conquer them as the Buddha would say now
they can't go and feed this wild animals
used to do you're the one in control so
the arm will get to eat only what the
mind who doesn't want any of it allows
it and whatever it allows you won't be
sensual thing because that has been
abandoned sensuality requires taking of
their wanting for granted that's why if
you stop wanting the wanting of sense
objects you get to see the extent of
that wanting in regard to the sense
object you get to understand is the
veloute gratification of it the extent
how far it can provide for you by seeing
that you get to understand the danger of
it right by not wanting the wanting of
sense objects you understood the danger
liable within wanting of the sense
objects
because say you say yes to the wanting
of pleasant sights for example and
within the next 10 seconds you go blind
all those sites are like quickly ripped
away from you pleasing person or or
whatever would you be affected of course
you would but if you've never given in
to the original haunting of those sight
sound smell taste touches would you be
affected you wouldn't because you never
took on that wanting you never welcomed
you didn't
that's the symbol of that mango tree but
a man climbs the mango tree to eat the
right mangos but then another man comes
and also say the mangos doesn't see the
other man who's eating up at the top but
he can't find the tree so he decided to
cut the tree down he decides to take
those sight sound smell taste touches
for himself
whichever way he deemed appropriate and
if that the other man who climbed the
tree doesn't come down quickly he's
gonna be destroyed hurt injured killed
or whatever and that's the nature
sensuality that directionality of
wanting the sense objects is always
directional as in he's always gonna take
you one way or the other which means you
can maintain the perspective on the
domain you have to commit to it and go
with it which then means you are not in
control and it's all well and good where
the things are going the way you kind of
wish them to go but it's inconceivable
that that's that's how they can always
be not just from the side of your own
senses failing or could fail or be
affected by accidents injuries and so on
illnesses but also the objects as well
millions of times
which is more there is just just a
schizo which is more the times I got
what I want
all the times I didn't get what I want
and you realize of course it's the times
I didn't get what I want
so whenever I go or they won't it was
kind of almost like oh wow
lucky accidental circumstantial on the
basis of more often not getting it but
if you stop if you stop wanting of any
type of wanting of the sense objects
you cannot not get what you want because
you only want one thing non-centrality
and that's not implied in sensuality the
sensuality keeps reminding you of your
freedom of sensuality sense objects
keeps reminding you of your
imperturbable state you can get what do
you mean by that if you see it on the
red level sure yeah you can't get no
wanting of sexuality just we I don't
want in charity because you don't know
what sensuality is to the full extent so
first you need to understand what
sensuality is which is what I explained
how we started this it's the one thing
of the sense objects not just the sense
objects or just the wanting it's the
wanting of these pleasing sight sound
smell taste touches it's this pressure
that I experience on the level of my
body on the level of my senses so you
stop wanting that wanting which means
you have to be you also have to stop
being concerned with the objects of your
sensuality but start looking at the
nature of sensuality which is it's being
wanted so you don't want that which is
being wanted in regards to the senses
succeed in that yeah then you can say I
don't want sensuality correctly did you
know what sensuality is unshakable peace
freedom from suffering
which is imperturbable especially mind
inconceivable in some ways
well it's inconceivable from the point
of view of the central domain so the
mind still takes centrality for grant it
doesn't see the extent of the central
domain the domain of imperturbable is
inconceivable body the mind starts
paying attention to dimensionality
discerning it and by doing so discerning
the domain that's freed from it the
domain of imperturbable
then it becomes conceivable it becomes
doable could you understood because
sensuality inherently in itself is
unpleasant it's dangerous it's a very
little gratification not worth even
making the effort for that clarification
it's like somebody asking you to pay the
lottery ticket thousand dollars and the
maximum win is five dollars why would
you do that it's ridiculous and that's
what's in Charlotte is the amount of
reward you get to the optimist most
refined society you can imagine it's
hundreds of your investment always every
single time that's why it's the Buddha
gave all those similes like a bone not
providing anything but adult concept
ringing it because you just mad with it
but they get nothing in return that's
the definition of sensuality of sensual
domain that's where it's a little
gratification it is not because you
didn't romantically pondered over it and
you you mused how the unsatisfactory no
factually that's the deal you get from
sensuality for the thousand pieces you
invested you get one in return
can you really wait a minute all I need
to do is not invest in this and I'll
gain thousandfold all I need to do is
practice renunciation and I gain
thousandfold all I need to do is not do
sensuality and I win and that's the
pleasure of John as well that relief
burden of pressure of freedom from
sensuality free from danger sensuality
not just that you invest a thousand
knowing well maybe not fully knowing but
in practice you get only one in return
Nevermore but even that you can lose your life on
but even that you can lose your life on
account of it
so not just that you don't get any
reward you actually get even taken even
more you could lose even more even the
you could lose even more even the
otherwise risk-free debt free and lost
free I was like a perfect advertisement
practice Jonathan but no it is it is so
whenever the blue states of little
gratification little peace again it's
it's a factual thing that he would be
describing and because centrality is of
little clarification little satisfaction
and much greater danger that's why if
you get to understand it you will
abandon it you cannot understand the
nature of sensuality correctly and still
wanted to a mutually exclusive
understanding of it means not wanting it
and that's why we would say the man who
engages with shoulders who seeks
happiness who won't happiness who want
joy so from this like that's why people
so from this like that's why people
engage with sensuality because that's
the only pleasure they know and that's
not necessarily the problem you use the
same criteria
I want pleasure the sense is one
pleasure that's fine but it's what
pleasure you assume with it that's the
difference and that's also where the
Buddha realized we said wait a minute
the pleasure of Jon the pleasure of
withdrawal or the pressure of
renunciation is nothing unwholesome body
so why would I fear the pleasure in
itself I won't fear this pleasure
because it's not unwholesome and then
that's that's what the other suitors
would say the man who wants pleasure
would then reflect and so because he
wants pleasure he will go to sensuality
but then you reflect and you realize
wait a minute I want pleasure which is
more pleasant investing thousand pieces
and getting one in return maybe or
refraining from investing anything and
keeping it all
oh so that's more pleasant so
even from the point of view of wanting
the pleasure of sensuality you will get
more through the straining that
sensuality
that's what sensuality and carelessness
go hand in hand
you need to be careless and lose the
sight of this perspective in order to be
pulled by sensuality and given but
that's the starting point
everybody starts by being careless in
being central within the central domain
so you start with a restraint in order
to develop perspective on it when you
know perspective then you can say no to
the right things
and that's why what we said in the other
toilets in Charlotte is fundamentally
not wanted by anyone know discerning
that you have bitterly just go with that
a reason wanting of your senses
but you appropriate it and then you
think you want it so you don't you don't
deny these sense objects you don't deny
the wanting of sense objects but you say
no to it and you let it endure without
giving in at any point of that duration
and then you realize the pain here the
unpleasant aspect is the aspect of sense
senses suffering on account of not
getting the object but now know that
neither that is mine
and then eventually those senses will
come down that's the Buddha gave the
similar of the five wild animals that
you tame in the beginning just peg them
onto like into a stake on the ground and
they're going to be pulling and ripping
in yanking and chewing and trying to
escape until they burn all the Energon
and they just sit and then they start to
listen and if that's not working for
somebody in Somis practice is because
they're probably still trying to either
deny the wanting of sense objects as an
interfere with it or are too concerned
with denying of the sense object
themselves this is which means whichever
way it is they don't have the
perspective on the nature of the sensual
domain but if you do then you realize no
it has a reason where its own sensuality
is their eyes want to see those wants to
smell and so on don't need to feel with
that just don't welcome it don't intend
it don't get careless in regard to they
won't be dragging only through you
giving in to it you get right yeah yeah
sure sure I see yeah no absolutely
so not wanting the one thing of sense
objects needs to be what needs to be
universal that attitude needs to be developed this
that attitude needs to be developed this
is not just for today and tomorrow that
I don't want this this is for the rest
of my life and any lives they might come
the wanting of sense objects will never
be wanted will never be welcomed
he might arise millions of times more
for you every time it arises every time
it is not welcomed and you don't open
the door and eventually it will have to
go away either way you will win you will
win by not being bothered by not losing
your your investment stupidly by not
exposing yourself to risk and then on
top of it by discerning the nature of
the imperturbable which in itself it's
immeasurably more pleasurable in a
wholesome sense like the pleasure of the
first jhana you can't even compare it to
the pleasure of sensuality is just
incomparable because two different
domains mutually exclusive you can't
have I have Jonathan I have sensuality
I have Jonathan I have sensuality
something like I engage the shotgun
exceptional and get jhanas no that's all
sensuality my friend
so discerning an abandoning of sensual
domain you discerned the main impact or
imperturbable in regard to that domain
and that's the pleasure of the jhanas exactly exactly
exactly exactly
oh please don't make the effort but when
I go back no which means that the future
possibility of welcoming sensuality you
welcome that and by welcoming the
possibility of sensuality you are still
fully engaged with ok I'm not going to
let you in today but we both know I'm
gonna open this door tomorrow and you
think this person will then go in the
meantime of course not yet that's the
whole point do not open the door so they
leave and never come back but the only
way they will do that is they really see
no he will never open the door you have
to convince the Mara's daughter
daughters and mara himself that the door
will never be open for them ever again
and how long that takes well that
depends on the power you